{"tossups": [{"question": "The Germanic Heruli tribe sacked this city, looting its <em>Stoa Poikile</em> [[stoh-AH poh-ee-KEE-leh]] and defacing art depicting the semi-legendary Battle of Oenoe [[ee-NOH-nee]]. The Sacred Way connected this city's district of Keremeikos to nearby Eleusis [[eh-LOO-siss]], where the Eleusinian [[eh-loo-SIH-nee-an]] Mysteries occurred. This city rebuilt its \"Long Walls\" after they were torn down by the victorious Spartans during the Peloponnesian War. The Acropolis contains the Parthenon of, for the point, what Greek city-state?", "answer": "<b><u>Athens</u></b> (or <b><u>Athenai</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Eighteen years after the first meeting in this city, a similar assembly was called for in Serdica. After his conversion to Christianity, Constantine summoned Christian bishops for a meeting in this city. Some of the decisions made at that meeting in this city included settling the date on which Easter should be celebrated, early decisions on Biblical canon, and a namesake creed. For the point, name this Bithynian [[bih-THIN-ee-an]] city that hosted two councils for the early Catholic church.", "answer": "<b><u>Nicaea</u></b> [[nye-SEE-ah]] (be lenient on pronunciation; accept pronunciations using a K sound for C; accept First Council of <b><u>Nicaea</u></b>; accept Second Council of <b><u>Nicaea</u></b>; accept <b><u>Nicene</u></b> Creed)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "He's not Tito, but this world leader's \"Third Way\" foreign policy courted both the U.S. and Soviet Union. Several of this leader's right-wing supporters killed Montoneros in the Ezeiza [[eh-ZEH-zah]] Massacre. This man's wife died of cancer after helping establish \"The Children's Republic\" theme park near Buenos Aires. The <em>descamisados</em> supported this man and his third wife, President Isabela. For the point, name this Argentine populist and president.", "answer": "Juan <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b> (or Juan Domingo <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this election, the Radical Democracy Party ran John C. Fr\u00e9mont on its ticket. Following the death of his friend, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Franklin Pierce declined a nomination for president during this election. The slogan \"Don't change horses in the middle of a stream\" was used during this election, which resulted in a loss for George McClellan. For the point, name this election during the Civil War, the second presidential victory for Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "<b><u>1864</u></b> United States presidential election", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While president, this reformer published articles anonymously in the <em>Ileri</em> [[ee-LEH-ree]] newspaper to promote nationalism. U.S. education reformer John Dewey was invited by this man to his nation in the mid-1920s, and this man banned the fez through the 1925 Hat Law. The Sheik Said [[SAH-eed]] rebellion, the first major Kurdish revolt, occurred during this man's administration. The Ottoman Empire was formally ended by, for the point, what reformer, the first president of the Republic of Turkey?", "answer": "Mustafa <b><u>Kemal</u><u>Ataturk</u></b> (accept either underlined portion; accept Mustafa <b><u>Kemal</u></b> Pasha)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A member of a cadet branch of this dynasty, Ferdinand II of the Two Sicilies, provided asylum for Pope Pius IX [[the Ninth]] after his ousting by the short-lived Roman Republic. The One Hundred Days of Napoleon briefly interrupted a \"Restoration\" named for this dynasty. The longest reigning monarch in European history, the \"Sun King\" Louis XIV [[the Fourteenth]] was of this dynasty. The Kingdoms of France and Spain were once controlled by, for the point, what dynasty of Louis XVI [[the Sixteenth]]?", "answer": "House of <b><u>Bourbon</u></b> (or <b><u>Bourbon</u></b> dynasty; or <b><u>Bourbon</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A network named for this good is used by economists to describe a \"Chinese Commonwealth,\" closely linking the PRC's business sector with that of Southeast Asia. Lamination of this good was performed by the Japanese to create the <em>yumi</em> bows wielded by feudal-era samurai. The introduction of paper by Cai Lun led to this good's replacement as a primary writing surface in the 2nd century. For the point, name this fast-growing plant, the primary food source of the panda.", "answer": "<b><u>Bamboo</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bamboo</u></b> Network)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This statesman briefly served as the initial chairman for the 9/11 Commission. Along with Le Duc Tho, this man won the 1973 Nobel Peace Prize for his efforts in negotiating a ceasefire in Vietnam. In 1971, this man embarked on a secret trip to meet with Premier Zhou Enlai and Mao Zedong, before returning on a public trip the following year. For the point, name this German-born U.S. Secretary of State who served under Richard Nixon and Gerald Ford.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Kissinger</u></b> (or Henry Alfred <b><u>Kissinger</u></b>; or Heinz Alfred <b><u>Kissinger</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Anne Curry wrote a \"New History\" of this battle, which was the subject of a mock 2010 tribunal in which justices such as Ruth Bader Ginsburg found its victor guilty of war crimes. The weight of mud on armor, as well as a system of stakes, disadvantaged one side in this battle. Charles d\u2019Albret [[sharl dahl-BREH]] was killed in this battle, which saw the mass death of French knights under fire from English longbowmen. For the point, identify this decisive 1415 victory for Henry V of England.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Agincourt</u></b> [[ah-zheen-KOHR]] (accept Battle of <b><u>Azincourt</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Polymath Abbas ibn Firnas may have been the first man to accomplish this feat using foreign silk. By performing this feat, the emperor's son Yuan Huangtou [[HWAHNG-TOH]] escaped imprisonment in Northern Qi [[CHEE]] territory. Eilmer of Malmesbury's love for the story of Daedalus [[DAY-dah-luss]] prompted him to attempt this feat in 11th-century England, traveling two hundred feet before crashing. For the point, name this feat accomplished by the Wright Brothers in Kitty Hawk, North Carolina in 1903.", "answer": "<b><u>Flight</u></b> (accept word forms or descriptions including the words <b><u>Fly</u></b>ing or <b><u>Gliding</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Peace Preservation Law banned one of these parties, which was cracked down on by a group nicknamed the \"Thought Police.\" Douglas MacArthur threatened to use violent force against this party's <em>Sanbetsu</em> arm during late 1940s strikes. With assistance from the Kuomintang, a party of this type defeated the various warlord cliques and resisted a Japanese invasion. The People's Republic of China is ruled by, for the point, which general type of party influenced by Marxist ideals?", "answer": "<b><u>Communist</u></b> Party (or <b><u>Communist</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Communism</u></b>; accept Japanese <b><u>Communist</u></b> Party; accept <b><u>Communist</u></b> Party of China; prompt on \"Socialist\" or \"Socialism\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Hugh Crawford provided an armed escort during the creation of this feature, which involved a tripod-mounted device called the Bird Transit. Tensions that ultimately led to the creation of this feature flared up during Cresap\u2019s [[KREE-saps]] War. An observatory built at the Star Gazers\u2019 Stone near the fork of the Brandywine was used to mark this boundary, which crosses the Susquehanna River. Created in 1763 to settle a dispute involving Lord Baltimore, for the point, what line resolved a boundary between Maryland and Pennsylvania?", "answer": "<b><u>Mason-Dixon</u></b> Line (accept <b><u>Mason and Dixon</u></b> Line; prompt on answers referencing the line between the North and the South)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In one war, this nation attempted to invade the Isonzo River Valley twelve times, each time being repelled by Austrian forces. This nation later stopped a Central Powers offensive at Monte Grappa, reversing their severe losses against German forces at Caporetto. After winning at Vittorio Veneto, this country occupied Trieste and the Tyrol. For the point, name this Mediterranean nation, formerly part of the Triple Alliance, that in 1915 joined the Allies during World War One.", "answer": "<b><u>Italy</u></b> (or <b><u>Italia</u></b>n Republic; or Repubblica <b><u>Italia</u></b>na; accept Kingdom of <b><u>Italy</u></b>; accept Regno d'<b><u>Italia</u></b>; accept <b><u>Italia</u></b>n Colonial Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Walter Cannon used these animals to support his theory of emotions by removing their sympathetic nervous systems. One of these animals named \"CC\" was a long-lived genetic clone born in 2001. A French one of these animals named F\u00e9licette [[FEH-lee-set]] was the only member of its species sent to space. One of these animals is simultaneously dead and alive in a thought experiment by Erwin Schr\u00f6dinger [[SHROH-ding-uh]]. For the point, name these scientifically-studied felines that were once worshipped in Ancient Egypt.", "answer": "Domestic <b><u>cat</u></b>s (or House <b><u>cat</u></b>s; accept Copy<b><u>Cat</u></b>; accept Schr\u00f6dinger's <b><u>cat</u></b>; accept <em>Felis</em> <em><b><u>cat</u></b>us</em>; accept <em><b><u>Felis</u></b></em> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "This empire used a system of royal couriers called <em>angoros</em> who were able to cover 1,600 miles in nine days. A postal system developed for this empire involved strategically placed relay stations, and was called Chapar Khaneh. This empire built the East-West \"Royal Road,\" connecting the Anatolian city of Sardis to the Median city of Susa. Governors called <em>satraps</em> were used by, for the point, what empire, which originated in modern Iran?", "answer": "First <b><u>Persia</u></b>n Empire; (accept <b><u>Achaemenid</u></b> [[ah-kuh-MEH-nid]] Empire; or <b><u>Achaemenid</u></b>s; or <b><u>X\u0161\u0101\u00e7a</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An early version of this script possibly appears in inscriptions on 26 Etruscan helmets found in Negau, though another theory claims this script derives from the Rhaetic alphabet. Elder Futhark used these letters, the longest inscription for which is found on the R\u00f6k stone, which features kennings common in skaldic poetry. Both Gothic and Italic origins have been proposed for, for the point, what alphabet once used to write Germanic languages?", "answer": "<b><u>Rune</u></b>s (or <b><u>Runic</u></b> alphabet; prompt on \"Italic\" or \"Gothic\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {"question": "After escaping the Little Bohemia Lodge, this man worked as a clerk under the alias of Jimmy Lawrence. This man\u2019s eventual arrest came after Ana Cump\u0103na\u0219 [[COOM-pah-nosh]], the owner of a brothel where this man was seeking refuge, turned him in. The BOI evolved into the FBI during the investigation into this man, who was declared the first Public Enemy Number One. For the point, name this Depression-era gangster who was killed outside Chicago's Biograph Theater.", "answer": "John Herbert <b><u>Dillinger</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In defiance of 2021 Parliamentary elections, supporters of the Fatah Alliance in this country have set-up \"protest camps\" near its heavily-guarded Green Zone in the Karkh district. During the Injar Offensive, cities in this country like Abu Ghraib [[AH-boo GRAYB]] and Fallujah [[fah-LOO-jah]] were seized by the insurgent Islamic State. In 2003, the United States toppled this country's regime of Saddam Hussein. The Gulf War was started by, for the point, what Mesopotamian country that invaded neighboring Kuwait?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Iraq</u></b> (or Jumhuriyat al-<b><u>Ir\u0101q</u></b>; or Komar-i <b><u>Eraq</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Confederate sympathizers from this nation led by Vernon Locke captured and commandeered a Union steamer in the Chesapeake Affair. Rebels from this nation led by William Lyon Mackenzie crossed into U.S. waters while aboard the <em>Caroline</em>, which was later burned by British forces. The death of Richard Montgomery occurred during an invasion of this nation, leading Benedict Arnold to head an ineffectual siege of Quebec City. For the point, name this northern neighbor of the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Canada</u></b> (accept Lower <b><u>Canada</u></b>; accept Upper <b><u>Canada</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This party claimed to adhere to \"New Nationalism\" and a \"Square Deal,\" becoming the only third party to finish ahead of the Republicans when that party nominated William H. Taft. In that election, this party's presidential candidate continued a campaign speech after being shot. This party earned its popular name after that candidate declared he was \"strong as a\" certain animal. For the point, name this party that nominated Theodore Roosevelt for U.S. president in 1912.", "answer": "<b><u>Progressive</u></b> Party (or <b><u>Progressive</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Bull Moose</u></b> Party)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Despite significant numerical inferiority, this ruler won the Battle of the Soor thanks to the insubordinate seizure of Burkersdorf by Ferdinand of Brunswick. This man's only serious loss came at Kunersdorf, though he was saved from destruction by Austrian and Russian hesitation, which he dubbed the \"Miracle of the House of Brandenburg.\" With victories at Chotusitz and Mollwitz, this ruler secured the region of Silesia in the War of the Austrian Succession. For the point, name this militaristic King of Prussia nicknamed \"the Great.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Frederick II</u></b> (accept <b><u>Frederick the Great</u></b>; prompt on \"Frederick\"; accept <b><u>Friedrich</u></b> in place of \"Frederick\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Carlos the Jackal bombed this city's Radio Free Europe headquarters in the late 1980s. Heinrich Himmler ordered the construction of Dachau thirty kilometers outside this city. During an operation called <em>Iqrit and Baram</em> [[ee-KREET and bah-RAHM]], Islamic extremists called Black September kidnapped Jewish athletes and held them hostage during the 1972 Olympics held in this city. For the point, name this Bavarian capital and site of the Beer Hall Putsch, the birthplace of Nazism.", "answer": "<b><u>Munich</u></b> (or <b><u>Munchen</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s assumption of the presidency occurred when he bested Rufus King of the Federalist Party in one election. As president, this man signed the Adams-Onis Treaty with Spain and signed the Missouri Compromise into law. This man promoted a namesake \"Doctrine\" which aimed to prevent European intervention in the Americas. For the point, name this last president of the \"Virginia Dynasty,\" the fifth president of the United States.", "answer": "James <b><u>Monroe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Evoking Roman history, one politician wrote that these battles were a sign that, \"the Die was cast, the Rubicon crossed,\" in his diary shortly before fleeing his Braintree home. Ralph Waldo Emerson wrote that the \"Shot heard round the world\" occurred at the beginning of these battles. Paul Revere's ride occurred immediately prior to, for the point, what set of 1775 skirmishes in Massachusetts which began the Revolutionary War?", "answer": "Battles of <b><u>Lexington</u></b> and <b><u>Concord</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; accept in either order)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Mass eviction of tenants during this event led to retaliations such as the shooting of Major Denis Mahon [[MAHN]]. \"Souperism\" was a movement during this event to convert starving families to Protestantism by providing them with food. This disaster was worsened by the policies of Prime Minister John Russell, which continued to export grain away from an affected island. For the point, name this 19th-century blight of a crop, which led to an Irish diaspora.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Famine</u></b> (accept <b><u>Great Hunger</u></b>; accept <b><u>Great Starvation</u></b>; accept Irish <b><u>Potato Famine</u></b>; prompt on \"Famine\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s forces used smoke bombs to entrap two princes named Mstislav [[meet-EE-slahv]] at the Battle of the Kalka River. This ruler became bitter rivals with his childhood friend, Jamukha, after their campaign against the Merkits. This ruler sent his lieutenant, Subutai to destroy the Khwarezmian Empire, and this man founded an empire that conquered the largest contiguous land area in history. Succeeded by his son Ogedei [[OH-geh-day]] and his grandson Kublai, for the point, who was this founder of the Mongol empire?", "answer": "<b><u>Genghis</u></b> Khan (or <b><u>Chengis</u></b> Khan; or <b><u>Tem\u00fcjin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1993, this sport was marred by tragedy when Monica Seles [[SEH-less]] was stabbed during a changeover. The original \"Battle of the Sexes\" in this sport saw Billie Jean King defeat Bobby Riggs in straight sets in 1973, but Jimmy Connors defeated Martina Navratilova in 1992. In 2021, controversy erupted when Peng Shuai [[PAHNG-SHWY]], a star in this sport, mysteriously disappeared after returning to China. For the point, name this sport whose oldest Grand Slam event is Wimbledon.", "answer": "<b><u>Tennis</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A trial concerning this organization and Steve Jackson Games resulted after this agency seized hundreds of floppy drives and private data concerning a joke server titled \"Illuminati.\" A member of this agency named Tim McCarthy was wounded by John Hinckley, Jr. during his assassination attempt of Ronald Reagan. For the point, name this agency under the Department of Homeland Security which protects political leaders of the U.S. including current and former presidents.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Secret Service</u></b> (accept <b><u>USSS</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In Geoffrey Chaucer\u2019s \u201cPardoner\u2019s Tale,\u201d he criticizes greedy men and doctors during this period. Another work of Chaucer's, <em>The Book of the Duchess</em>, mourns the death of Blanche of Castile, Henry IV\u2019s mother, during this time period. <em>La Danse Macabre</em>, or \u201cthe Dance of Death\u201d was a genre that originated during this historical period. The frame story of Boccaccio's <em>Decameron</em> is about ten people who flee Florence during, for the point, what pandemic that wiped out a third of Europe's population?", "answer": "<b><u>Black Death</u></b> (or <b><u>Bubonic Plague</u></b>; accept The <b><u>Pestilence</u></b>; or <b><u>Great Mortality</u></b>; prompt on \"plague\")", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This man won the 1904 Nobel Prize in Physiology after publishing <em>The Work of the</em> <em>Digestive Glands</em> and earned his PhD after presenting research on what he termed \"nervism.\" Although he also used stimuli like shocks, this man's best known experiment involved ringing a bell to indicate that food was ready for a group of dogs. For the point, name this Russian scientist known for developing the idea of classical conditioning.", "answer": "Ivan <b><u>Pavlov</u></b> (or Ivan Petrovich <b><u>Pavlov</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "The mass rejection of this movement's early works by the likes of Johan Jongkind and Camille Pissarro [[pee-sah-ROH]] occurred at the \"Salon of the Refused\" partly due to protests reaching the traditionalist Napoleon III. A painter in this movement depicted Republican France's first instance of the \"Celebration of Peace\" holiday in the painting <em>The</em> <em>Rue Mosnier</em> [[ROO-mohs-NYEH]] <em>Dressed with Flags</em>. The nude painting <em>Olympia</em> by \u00c9douard Manet is an example of, for the point, what art movement whose other members include Claude Monet?", "answer": "<b><u>Impression</u></b>ism (accept <b><u>Impression</u></b>ist)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Prosecutor Natalia Poklonskaya [[pohk-lohn-SKY-yah]] attempted to ban this region's <em>Mejlis</em> [[MEHJ-leess]] autonomous assemblies, forcing legislators to flee north. Using cattle trains, Lavrentiy Beria and the NKVD emptied this region of its Tatar minority due to largely false claims they collaborated with the Nazis. In 2014, this autonomous region declared independence for one day until its annexation by the Russian Federation. For the point, name this peninsula, formerly controlled by Ukraine.", "answer": "<b><u>Crimea</u></b>n Peninsula (prompt on \"Ukraine\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of the namesakes of this case wrongly convicted Randal Dale Adams for murder. The companion case to this one involved Sandra Cano [[kah-NOH]] and her attorney, Margie Pitts Hames. Harry Blackmun quoted Joseph McKenna's \"capable of repetition, yet evading review\" exception in this case. Sarah Weddington and Linda Coffee raised challenges that led to this case, in which Norma McCorvey was the plaintiff under a pseudonym. Decided alongside <em>Doe v. Bolton</em>, for the point, what was this 1973 decision to legalize abortion?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Roe v. Wade</u></b></em> (accept in either order; accept <em>Jane</em> <em><b><u>Roe</u></b>, et al.</em> <em><b><u>v.</u></b> Henry</em> <em><b><u>Wade</u></b>, District</em> <em>Attorney of Dallas County</em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The only original, typewritten manuscript of this oration was given to a volunteer security guard, Villanova basketball star George Raveling [[RAV-eh-ling]]. This speech references the Emancipation Proclamation, claiming that \"One hundred years later, the Negro is still not free.\" A quarter of a million civil rights supporters were present outside the Lincoln Memorial during, for the point, which 1963 oration by Martin Luther King, Jr.?", "answer": "<b><u>I Have a Dream</u></b> Speech (or the <b><u>Speech during the March on Washington</u></b>; accept MLK's <b><u>speech at the Lincoln Memorial</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This structure's nickname may derive from a boxer named Caunt or an engineer named Hall. Augustus Pugin [[PYOO-jin]] designed this landmark as part of Charles Barry's rebuilding project following an 1834 fire. A melody that is emitted from this landmark every fifteen minutes is known as the \"Westminster Quarters,\" and the sound of this structure's hourly ringing introduces news on both ITV and the BBC. For the point, give this common name for the Great Bell of the clock tower on London's Palace of Westminster.", "answer": "<b><u>Big Ben</u></b> (accept <b><u>Elizabeth Tower</u></b> before \"Bell\" is mentioned; prompt on descriptive answers referencing the tower or the bell in the tower of the Palace of Westminster)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "During this man's tenure as president of Princeton University, playwright Eugene O'Neill was expelled for throwing a rock at his window. Under this man's administration, the Palmer Raids were launched to arrest radical leftists. This man's ran for re-election by insisting that \"He Kept Us Out of War,\" though he ironically declared war on Germany four months into his second term. For the point, name this 28th president of the United States who served during World War One.", "answer": "Woodrow <b><u>Wilson</u></b> (or Thomas Woodrow <b><u>Wilson</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}